<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<compendium version="5'>"
<!--Spell Attack rolls assume PROF added to roll, not applicable for Ranged while engaged in Melee range-->
<!--replaced ":" as intro to list with ".", and as in-line text with " - "-->
  <spell>
    <name>Catnap (XGtE)</name>
    <level>3</level>
    <school>EN</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>30 feet</range>
    <components>S, M (a pinch of sand)</components>
    <duration>10 minutes</duration>
    <classes>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</classes>
    <text>You make a calming gesture, and up to three willing creatures of your choice that you can see within range fall unconscious for the spell’s duration. The spell ends on a target early if it takes damage or someone uses an action to shake or slap it awake. If a target remains unconscious for the full duration, that target gains the benefit of a short rest, and it can’t be affected by this spell again until it finishes a long rest.</text>
    <text />
    <text>At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, you can target one additional willing creature for each slot level above 3rd.</text>
    <text />
    <text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Cause Fear (XGtE)</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <school>N</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components>V</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <classes>Warlock, Wizard</classes>
    <text>You awaken the sense of mortality in one creature you can see within range. A construct or an undead is immune to this effect. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or become frightened of you until the spell ends. The frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
    <text />
    <text>At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above lst. The creatures must be within 30 feet of each other when you target them.</text>
    <text />
    <text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Ceremony (XGtE)</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <school>A (ritual)</school>
    <time>1 hour</time>
    <range>Touch</range>
    <components>V, S, M (25 gp worth of powdered silver, which the spell consumes)</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Cleric, Paladin</classes>
    <text>You perform a special religious ceremony that is infused with magic. When you cast the spell, choose one of the following rites, the target of which must be within 10 feet of you throughout the casting.</text>
    <text />
    <text>Atonement: You touch one willing creature whose alignment has changed, and you make a DC 20 Wisdom (Insight) check. On a successful check, you restore the target to its original alignment.</text>
    <text />
    <text>Bless water: You touch one vial of water and cause it to become holy water.</text>
    <text />
    <text>Coming of Age: You touch one vial of water and cause it to become holy water.</text>
    <text />
    <text>Dedication: You touch one humanoid who wishes to be dedicated to your god’s service. For the next 24 hours, whenever the target makes a saving throw, it can roll a d4 and add the number rolled to the save. A creature can benefit from this rite only once.</text>
    <text />
    <text>Funeral Rite: You touch one corpse, and for the next 7 days, the target can’t become undead by any means short of a wish spell.</text>
    <text />
    <text>Wedding: You touch adult humanoids willing to be bonded together in marriage. For the next 7 days, each target gains a +2 bonus to AC while they are within 30 feet of each other. A creature can benefit from this rite again only if widowed.</text>
    <text />
    <text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
    <roll></roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Chaos Bolt (XGtE)</name>
    <level>1</level>
    <school>EV</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>120 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <classes>Sorcerer</classes>
    <text>You hurl an undulating, warbling mass of chaotic energy at one creature in range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 2d8 + 1d6 damage. Choose one of the dSs. The number rolled on that die determines the attacks damage type, as shown below.</text>
    <text />
    <text>d8 / Damage Type</text>
    <text />
    <text>1: Acid</text>
    <text />
    <text>2: Cold</text>
    <text />
    <text>3: Fire</text>
    <text />
    <text>4: Force</text>
    <text />
    <text>5: Lightning</text>
    <text />
    <text>6: Poison</text>
    <text />
    <text>7: Psychic</text>
    <text />
    <text>8: Thunder</text>
    <text />
    <text>If you roll the same number on both d8s, the chaotic energy leaps from the target to a different creature of your choice within 30 feet of it. Make a new attack roll against the new target, and make a new damage roll, which could cause the chaotic energy to leap again. A creature can be targeted only once by each casting of this spell.</text>
    <text />
    <text>At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, each target takes 1d6 extra damage of the type rolled for each slot level above 1st.</text>
    <text />
    <text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
    <roll>1d8, 1d6</roll>
  </spell>
  <spell>
    <name>Charm Monster (XGtE)</name>
    <level>4</level>
    <school>E</school>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>30 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>1 hour</duration>
    <classes>Bard, Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</classes>
    <text>You attempt to charm a creature you can see within range. It must make a Wisdom saving throw, and it does so with advantage if you or your companions are fighting it. If it fails the saving throw, it is charmed by you until the spell ends or until you or your companions do anything harmful to it. The charmed creature is friendly to you. When the spell ends, the creature knows it was charmed by you.</text>
    <text />
    <text>At Higher Levels: When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 4th. The creatures must be within 30 feet of each other when you target them.</text>
    <text />
    <text>This spell can be found in Xanathar's Guide to Everything</text>
  </spell>
</compendium>